A Guide to the Richmond Croom Beatty papers, 1925-1967
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Richmond Croom Beatty papers, 1925-1967
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 2
1.5 linear feet
Richmond Croom Beatty
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated to the Department by Mrs. Floy Beatty in 1972.
Biographical/Historical Information
Richmond Croom Beatty (1905-1961) professor and writer, usually associated with Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee, was the author of biographies of Bayard Taylor (1936), Lord Macaulay (1938), and James Russell Lowell (1942); edited The American Tradition in Literature (1957); also wrote poetry, articles and reviews.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence with publishers and friends, manuscripts of articles, poems, books, reviews, and other writings, notes, teaching notebooks, term papers, clippings, printed materials, and photographs. Includes translation from the German version of William Byrd's Natural History of Virginia, which Beatty edited and published. Correspondents include Stringfellow Barr, Louise Cowan, Wilbur Cross, Harold M. Jones, Merrill Moore, Jesse Stuart and R.M. Weaver. Also donated were approximately 215 books, the majority about or by southern writers, especially Tennesseeans. Some of the volumes are inscribed by the authors to Beatty. The majority of Beatty's own works are in the collection and autographed. A list of the titles donated is included at the end of the guide.
Arrangement
These papers are divided into two series: Series 1: Personal Papers, 1925-1960 and Series 2: Publications 1932-1967.
Files are arranged topically within each series.
Contents List
- Series 1: Personal Papers, 1925-1960
  - College Term Papers, 1927-1930 (Box-folder 1:1-1:2)
  - Poetry, undated (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Manuscript of William Byrd's Natural History of Virginia, circa 1940 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - General Correspondence, 1930 1960 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Assorted short manuscripts and notes, undated (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Photographs of Beatty and Bayard Taylor, undated (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Works of other people, 1925, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1:8-2.1)
  - Modern Poetry Notebook and Contents, 1942 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Novel Draft Notebook, undated (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Notebooks of Transcribed Nineteenth-Century Correspondence of James Russell Lowell, circa 1930s (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Notebook of Transcribed Excerpts from Periodicals, undated (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Notebook of Transcribed Excerpts from an Unidentified Mid-Twentieth-Century Journal, undated (Box-folder 2:6)
- Series 2: Periodicals, 1932-1967
  - The Atlantic Monthly, 1932 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Forum and Century, 1932 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - The General Magazine and Historical Chronicle, 1932 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - The Hopkins Review, 1951 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - The Observer, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - The Paris Review, 1953 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - The New Republic, 1934 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - River, 1937 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Shenandoah, 1952 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Southern Observer, 1954 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - The Southwestern Journal, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Vanderbilt University Alumnus and Press Release, 1949, 1967 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - The Virginia Quarterly Review, 1958 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Excerpt from South Atlantic Bulletin, 1937 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Excerpt from Studies in Philology, 1940 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Reprints from Philological Quarterly, 1934 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Reprint from Publications of the Modern Language Association of America, 1934 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Reprint from The Sewanee Review, 1941 (Box-folder 3:18)